Every ant has his day.
Antz is a animation, family, comedy film directed by Eric Darnell.
A neurotic worker ant in love with a rebellious princess rises to
unlikely stardom when he switches places with a soldier.
Signing up to march in a parade, he ends up under the
command of a bloodthirsty general.
But he's actually been enlisted to fight against a termite army.
Z-4195 “Z” (voice), played by Woody Allen.
Princess Bala (voice), played by Sharon Stone.
Chip (voice), played by Dan Aykroyd.
Queen (voice), played by Anne Bancroft.
Barbatus (voice), played by Danny Glover.
General Mandible (voice), played by Gene Hackman.
Antz is a 1998 American animated adventure comedy film directed by Eric Darnell and
Tim Johnson, and written by Todd Alcott, Chris Weitz and Paul Weitz.
Produced by DreamWorks Animation and PDI, the film features an ensemble voice cast, including Woody Allen, Sharon Stone,
Jennifer Lopez, Sylvester Stallone, Christopher Walken, Dan Aykroyd, Anne Bancroft, Danny Glover and Gene Hackman.
Some of the main characters share facial
similarities with the actors who voice them.
The film involves an anxious worker ant, Z, who
falls in love with Princess Bala.
When the arrogant General Mandible attempts to seize control of the ant colony, Z must
combine his desire for purpose with his inner strength to save everyone.
Development began in 1988 when Walt Disney Feature Animation pitched a film called Army Ants, about a
pacifist worker ant teaching lessons of independent thinking to his militaristic colony.
Meanwhile, Jeffrey Katzenberg had left the company in a feud with CEO Michael Eisner
over the vacant president position after the death of Frank Wells.
Katzenberg would later go on to help co-found DreamWorks with Steven Spielberg and David Geffen,
and the three planned to rival Disney with the company's new animation division.
Production began in May 1996.
DreamWorks had contracted Pacific Data Images (PDI) to begin working
on computer-animated films to rival Pixar's features.
During its production, a controversial public feud erupted between Katzenberg of DreamWorks and Steve Jobs and John
Lasseter of Pixar, due to the production of their similar film A Bug's Life, which was released a month later.
The feud worsened when Disney refused to avoid competition with
DreamWorks' intended first animated release, The Prince of Egypt.
Harry Gregson-Williams and John Powell composed the music for the film.
Antz premiered at the Toronto International Film Festival on September 19, 1998, and was
released theatrically in the United States on October 2 by DreamWorks Distribution.
It grossed $172 million on a budget of $42–105 million and received positive reviews from
critics, who praised the voice cast, animation, humor, and its appeal towards adults.
The film explores themes of princess, work, worker, hero, general.
The tone is lighthearted.